Guide to the Jesse Sublett Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Jesse Sublett Papers
1978-1995
The Wittliff Collections https://www.thewittliffcollections.txstate.edu
Sublett, Jesse
SWWC.027
1.5 Linear Feet
3 boxes
Book manuscripts, screenplays, drafts, cartoons, clippings, correspondence, photographs, ephemera, sound recordings, and artifacts documenting Sublett's careers as a rock musician and writer.
Scope and Contents
Book manuscripts, screenplays, drafts, cartoons, clippings, correspondence, photographs, ephemera, sound recordings, and artifacts documenting Sublett's careers as a rock musician and writer. Many of the drafts of Sublett's writings include handwritten annotations by the author. Copies of certain letters to Richard Holland, former Curator of the Southwestern Writers Collection, have been retained when they shed light on Sublett's creative life.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jesse Sublett, 1993-1995.
Biographical Notes
Jesse Sublett was born May 15, 1954, in Johnson City, Texas. He was valedictorian of Johnson City's LBJ High School Class of 1972, and attended Southwest Texas State University from 1972-1974 as an English major.
From 1974 until 1986 Sublett lived in Austin, where he played a dominant role in defining the live music scene as bass player and/or lead singer for a number of bands, most notably The Skunks, who recorded three records between 1978 and 1983.
During this time, Sublett began writing short pieces for the Austin Chronicle, including record and restaurant reviews, and in 1984 he was assigned to write a short piece on the club circuit which bands like The Skunks played. Instead, he submitted a semi-parodic music mystery entitled "Traveling the Hardboiled Highway," which imitated the style of a hardboiled detective novel. This marked the birth of Martin Fender, the central character in Sublett's first three novels. He submitted a second Fender piece, "The Nature of the Crime," which the Chronicle's editorial staff declined to publish but which they encouraged him to re-work as a novel. After finishing the re-titled Capitol Crimes, he wrote Rock Critic Murders with the intention of selling the two novels as a series. While waiting for the attention of publishers on the first two books, he began work on a third novel, Blunt Instrument. In 1987 he moved to Los Angeles in order to be closer to the spirit of his hero Raymond Chandler. He continued to play music on the West Coast while awaiting responses from publishers and re-writing Blunt Instrument. Shortly thereafter, Lisa Kaufman at Viking took an interest in his work and agreed to publish Rock Critic Murders. Sublett has written several screenplays, and served as story editor for the Disney series Adventures of the Old West. During 1994-1995 he ventured into nonfiction, writing a history of the Texas Turnpike Authority.
Sublett now lives in Austin with his wife Lois Richwine, their son Dashiell, and two cats.
Index Terms
Subjects
Detective and mystery stories; Authors, American -- Texas -- 20th century; Rock musicians
Subjects (Persons)
Sublett, Jesse
- Early Works, 1985-1998
  Series Description
  This series, kept as a discrete group of materials by Sublett in his home, contains drafts of some of his short pieces for the Austin Chronicle, including The Nature of the Crime (1984), a piece never published but which prompted the Chronicle's editorial staff to urge Sublett to write a novel. The rest of the items relate to Rock Critic Murders: consent and release forms,an early title page design containing a saguaro cactus, and blurbs solicited from James Ellroy, Gerald Petievich, and Kinky Friedman.
  - Various annotated drafts including, "The Nature of the Crime," consent and release forms, title pages, and blurbs, for Rock Critic Murders. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Austin Chronicle, 1983-1985
  Articles and stories appearing in the Austin Chronicle: "The Big Tape", "X-15: The 4-Track Walkman", and "Crying on the Shoulder of the Road" (November 24, 1983); "Traveling the Hardboiled Highway", record review: Madonna (March 23, 1984); "How to Make a Record" (November 30, 1984); "Martin Fender & the Flat-Top Kid", short piece on Raymond Chandler for a feature on mystery writers (December 13, 1985).
  - Photocopies of stories appearing in The Austin Chronicle (Originals are in Box 3, Folder 8) (Box 1, Folder 2, Box 3, Folder 8)
- Novels, 1984-1987
  Contains a letter to Richard Holland explaining the sequence of Sublett's works; a 2nd draft of Rock Critic Murders, a first draft of the book which ultimately became Tough Baby entitled Blunt Instrument, and a completely-rewritten second draft of Tough Baby entitled The Big Hurt.
  - Letter to Richard Holland explaining Sublett's creative process, February 11, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Annotated typescript of Rock Critic Murders (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Annotated typescript of Tough Baby, version titled Blunt Instrument (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - Annotated typescript of Tough Baby, version titled The Big Hurt (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Screenplays, 1988-1993
  Contains a short note to Richard Holland describing Hale Storm as a first draft, and versions of Hey Joe, Rock Critic Murders, Pay the Devil, Hale Storm, Shadows in the Sun, (with Stephen Purvis), and two versions of In the West (with Stephen Purvis and Tom Huckabee).
  - Letter to Richard Holland regarding scripts, April 12, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Master copy of script titled Hey Joe (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Master copy of script titled Rock Critic Murders (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Master copy of script titled Play the Devil (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - First draft of script titled Hale Storm, June 14, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - First draft of script titled Shadows in the Sun, February 11, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Script titled In the West (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Final Shooting Script for In the West, revised, March 27 - April 17, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Non-Fiction, 1995
  Notes and drafts for History of the Texas Turnpike Authority.
  - Annotated typescript of The History of the Texas Turnpike Authority (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Reviews and Publicity, 1982-1992
  Interviews, reviews, and notices documenting both Sublett's music career and his writing career.
  - Photocopies of clippings relating to Sublett's writing and activities with the band The Skunks (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1978-1990
  Candid shots and publicity photos of Sublett and the Skunks.
  - Several black and white photographs of The Skunks, Sublett, and one unidentified young boy in a cowboy hat and bandanna (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Ephemera, 1982-1992
  Posters and postcards advertising the Skunks, Boiled in Concrete, a novel by Andrew Vachss, and a magazine cover for which Sublett modeled.
  - Postcard advertising for Boiled in Concrete by Sublett, and Another Chance to Get it Right by Andrew Vachs, Christmas card from The Skunks, ad for Online Data Access magazine, The Skunks debut album poster, "Jesse Sublett's Secret Six" poster, clubfoot debut poster for "Jesse Sublett's Secret Six," Skunks last show poster, Boiled in Concrete poster. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Sound Recordings, 1979-1982
  1 45-rpm record; 1 2-record set (with lyrics); 1 cassette representing the recorded output of the Skunks.
  - Album cover for The Skunks special edition six song release, album titled, "What do you want…The Racket," album containing songs, "Gimme Some," and, "Promises," album containing songs, "Something about you scares me," and, "Cheap Girl," lyrics sheet dated 1979 with lyrics to various songs (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Artifacts, 1978-1982
  Artifacts from Sublett's musical career.
  - Two metal buttons, one pink and one black, on which "The Skunks" has been printed, two t-shirts, one black bearing the label "The Skunks" one red bearing label "KLBJ FM PRESENTS THE SKUNKS…," black and white leather shoes worn by Sublett (Box 3, Folder 7)